<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-03T18:43:28+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ignacio Calvo Blog</title><subtitle>Professional developer and amateur musician.</subtitle><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Listing environment variables with Powershell</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software/2023/01/19/listing-environment-variables-with-powershell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Listing environment variables with Powershell" /><published>2023-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software/2023/01/19/listing-environment-variables-with-powershell</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software/2023/01/19/listing-environment-variables-with-powershell.html">A pretty basic Powershell command that everyone uses to list environment variables is:

```powershell
ls env:
```

A few caveats here: this is NOT going to work in Linux or MacOS because in those environments the alias `ls` is not defined[^1]. Therefore the safest bet is to use `Get-ChildItem` instead.

Also, this is shown in table format (which is nice), but it truncates long values (which is not nice with variables like `PATH`):

![Table format with truncate](/assets/img/2013-01-19-1.png)

In order to avoid that we can re-format the output in this way:

```powershell
Get-ChildItem env: | Format-Table -Wrap
```

This will show a long value like this:
![Table format with wrap](/assets/img/2013-01-19-2.png)

Finally, if you miss the classical format you get from Linux `env` or Windows CMD `set`, you can do the following:

```powershell
Get-ChildItem env: | % { &quot;$($_.Name)=$($_.Value)&quot; }
```

It shows like this:
![Classical format](/assets/img/2013-01-19-3.png)

[^1]: [Microsoft Powershell Aliases Documentation](https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/powershell/scripting/learn/shell/using-aliases?view=powershell-7.3)</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="software" /><category term="powershell" /><category term="linux" /><summary type="html">A pretty basic Powershell command that everyone uses to list environment variables is:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Generating thumbnails for a music score</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software/2021/04/08/imagemagick.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generating thumbnails for a music score" /><published>2021-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software/2021/04/08/imagemagick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software/2021/04/08/imagemagick.html">At the beginning of this year I started to prepare my [new showcase of musical works]({% link music/index.markdown %}). After some iterations I thought it would be a great idea to create backgrounds for each work, based on its score sheet. But, being a developer (that&apos;s synonym for lazy), I didn&apos;t want to prepare those thumbnails manually. So I wondered if there was some way to take a PDF file, cut an specific part of the first page, and apply a number of transformations to get a beautiful background that didn&apos;t contrast a lot with the text and elements that I would place on top of that.

In the beginning I imagined that I would need some tool for extracting an image from that PDF and a different one that allowed me to do the graphical transformations. I was not exactly wrong on that, although I finally solved the problem with call to a single command line tool. A bit of a paradox? Not so much.

The tool that everyone of you should know for doing programmatic digital image processing is [ImageMagick](https://imagemagick.org/). This amazing tools allow you to take any number of graphical inputs (or even creating empty canvases) and transform them in any way you could imagine. The aforementioned paradox is explained because, in order to use a PDF as input, you need a different software already installed, the legendary [Ghostscript](https://www.ghostscript.com/).

ImageMagick works by applying operations in order. You can do tons of transformations, add layers and combine them, etc.

The following is the call I do to generate my thumbnails:

```powershell
magick `
  &quot;$input&quot; `
  -density 300 `
  -background white ` # PDF image comes with transparent background, so we set a white background, and...
  -alpha remove ` # ...we remove the alpha channel.
  -distort SRT &apos;-5&apos; ` # rotate 5 degrees counter-clockwise
  -resize 400 ` # resize to 400px wide
  -crop 340x340+10+10 +repage ` # crop a 340x340 rectangle, offset 10px down and 10px left
  -background gray ` # set a gray background for the...
  -vignette 0x100+0+0 ` # vignette effect (obscure image borders creating a round shadow)
  -fill &quot;rgb(255,240,100)&quot; -colorize 20 ` # colorize with a yellowish tone
  -channel RGB -function polynomial 0.6,0.4 ` # Reduce contrast by applying a transformation function
  -attenuate 0.3 +noise Gaussian ` # add a bit of noise to add texture
  &quot;$output&quot;
```</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="software" /><category term="thumbnail" /><category term="music" /><category term="score" /><category term="pdf" /><summary type="html">At the beginning of this year I started to prepare my new showcase of musical works. After some iterations I thought it would be a great idea to create backgrounds for each work, based on its score sheet. But, being a developer (that’s synonym for lazy), I didn’t want to prepare those thumbnails manually. So I wondered if there was some way to take a PDF file, cut an specific part of the first page, and apply a number of transformations to get a beautiful background that didn’t contrast a lot with the text and elements that I would place on top of that. In the beginning I imagined that I would need some tool for extracting an image from that PDF and a different one that allowed me to do the graphical transformations. I was not exactly wrong on that, although I finally solved the problem with call to a single command line tool. A bit of a paradox? Not so much. The tool that everyone of you should know for doing programmatic digital image processing is ImageMagick. This amazing tools allow you to take any number of graphical inputs (or even creating empty canvases) and transform them in any way you could imagine. The aforementioned paradox is explained because, in order to use a PDF as input, you need a different software already installed, the legendary Ghostscript. ImageMagick works by applying operations in order. You can do tons of transformations, add layers and combine them, etc. The following is the call I do to generate my thumbnails: magick ` &quot;$input&quot; ` -density 300 ` -background white ` # PDF image comes with transparent background, so we set a white background, and... -alpha remove ` # ...we remove the alpha channel. -distort SRT &apos;-5&apos; ` # rotate 5 degrees counter-clockwise -resize 400 ` # resize to 400px wide -crop 340x340+10+10 +repage ` # crop a 340x340 rectangle, offset 10px down and 10px left -background gray ` # set a gray background for the... -vignette 0x100+0+0 ` # vignette effect (obscure image borders creating a round shadow) -fill &quot;rgb(255,240,100)&quot; -colorize 20 ` # colorize with a yellowish tone -channel RGB -function polynomial 0.6,0.4 ` # Reduce contrast by applying a transformation function -attenuate 0.3 +noise Gaussian ` # add a bit of noise to add texture &quot;$output&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quintet movement, Op. 31, updated</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/26/quintet-updated.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quintet movement, Op. 31, updated" /><published>2021-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/26/quintet-updated</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/26/quintet-updated.html">I&apos;ve made a number of updates to [Quintet movement, Op. 31]({% link music/quintet_movement/index.markdown %}). Mainly bowings, alterations, and other notation issues. Some reworking of the &quot;tango&quot; solos.</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="composition" /><category term="music" /><summary type="html">I’ve made a number of updates to Quintet movement, Op. 31. Mainly bowings, alterations, and other notation issues. Some reworking of the “tango” solos.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Added comments in music works</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/25/music-works-comments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Added comments in music works" /><published>2021-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/25/music-works-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/03/25/music-works-comments.html">I&apos;ve added a comments section in all the pages of my music works. So you can head e.g. to [Waltz Miniature, Op. 1]({% link music/waltz_miniature/index.markdown %}) and drop a comment if you want!</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="composition" /><category term="music" /><category term="comments" /><summary type="html">I’ve added a comments section in all the pages of my music works. So you can head e.g. to Waltz Miniature, Op. 1 and drop a comment if you want!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MIDI Recorder</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/software/2021/03/20/midi-recorder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MIDI Recorder" /><published>2021-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/software/2021/03/20/midi-recorder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/software/2021/03/20/midi-recorder.html">I&apos;ve just released a command line utility to record MIDI activity and save it into files. The files are split by some delay without MIDI activity. You can have this tool running in the background and it will quietly save all those improvisations that are usually lost and that you cannot remember well afterwards!

Please go to [MIDI Recorder site](https://github.com/MidiRecorder/MidiRecorder/) for more information and downloads.</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="software" /><category term="composition" /><category term="music" /><category term="midi" /><category term="recorder" /><summary type="html">I’ve just released a command line utility to record MIDI activity and save it into files. The files are split by some delay without MIDI activity. You can have this tool running in the background and it will quietly save all those improvisations that are usually lost and that you cannot remember well afterwards! Please go to MIDI Recorder site for more information and downloads.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Music works</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/01/19/music-works.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Music works" /><published>2021-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/2021/01/19/music-works</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/2021/01/19/music-works.html">Since I&apos;ve [started using Sibelius+Noteperformer]({% post_url /studiodiary/2020-11-01-purchased-noteperformer %}), I&apos;ve been working on rearranging and making decent score editions of my past works, before moving on and composing new things. It&apos;s still work in progress but I&apos;ve made some advances.

I&apos;ve created a new page with the [complete list of my works]({% link music/index.markdown %}). Right new all the music work pages are a bit empty, except for the first one I added: the [Waltz Miniature, Op.1]({% link music/waltz_miniature/index.markdown %}). Please check the piece out!</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="composition" /><category term="music" /><summary type="html">Since I’ve started using Sibelius+Noteperformer, I’ve been working on rearranging and making decent score editions of my past works, before moving on and composing new things. It’s still work in progress but I’ve made some advances. I’ve created a new page with the complete list of my works. Right new all the music work pages are a bit empty, except for the first one I added: the Waltz Miniature, Op.1. Please check the piece out!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Purchased NotePerformer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/11/01/purchased-noteperformer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Purchased NotePerformer" /><published>2020-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/11/01/purchased-noteperformer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/11/01/purchased-noteperformer.html">I&apos;ve purchased [NotePerfomer 3](https://www.noteperformer.com/), which is a playback engine for notation software (Sibelius, Finale and Dorico). I think it&apos;s an absolutely extraordinary product.

I can forget about sample libraries, controllers, keyswitches, and simply write notes in a staff. It still doesn&apos;t reach the quality of a handcrafted arrangement with a DAW, but there&apos;s no reason to think it cannot get there at some point. It is my belief that automating as much as possible all the nitty-gritty details of virtual instrument arrangement is the way to go.

And the price tag is awesome as well!</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="studiodiary" /><category term="audio" /><category term="home" /><category term="studio" /><category term="recording" /><summary type="html">I’ve purchased NotePerfomer 3, which is a playback engine for notation software (Sibelius, Finale and Dorico). I think it’s an absolutely extraordinary product. I can forget about sample libraries, controllers, keyswitches, and simply write notes in a staff. It still doesn’t reach the quality of a handcrafted arrangement with a DAW, but there’s no reason to think it cannot get there at some point. It is my belief that automating as much as possible all the nitty-gritty details of virtual instrument arrangement is the way to go. And the price tag is awesome as well!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Desktop arrived!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/09/01/desktop-arrived.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Desktop arrived!" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/09/01/desktop-arrived</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/09/01/desktop-arrived.html">After lots of delays, I&apos;ve finally received desktop (a [Glorious Sound Desk Pro](https://www.glorious.de/glorious-sound-desk-pro-black)). I have also reorganized my studio a bit by setting the desktop against the wall instead of against the window. This is a much better placement.</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="studiodiary" /><category term="audio" /><category term="home" /><category term="studio" /><category term="recording" /><summary type="html">After lots of delays, I’ve finally received desktop (a Glorious Sound Desk Pro). I have also reorganized my studio a bit by setting the desktop against the wall instead of against the window. This is a much better placement.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Purchased new Desktop</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/06/04/purchased-desktop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Purchased new Desktop" /><published>2020-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/06/04/purchased-desktop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/06/04/purchased-desktop.html">I&apos;ve ordered a new desktop, a beautiful [Glorious Sound Desk Pro](https://www.glorious.de/glorious-sound-desk-pro-black) in black.</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="studiodiary" /><category term="audio" /><category term="home" /><category term="studio" /><category term="recording" /><summary type="html">I’ve ordered a new desktop, a beautiful Glorious Sound Desk Pro in black.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Purchased SSD and Novation Impulse 61</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/04/23/new-ssd-and-novation-impulse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Purchased SSD and Novation Impulse 61" /><published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/04/23/new-ssd-and-novation-impulse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/music/studiodiary/2020/04/23/new-ssd-and-novation-impulse.html">Two new additions for my home studio: a much needed 1TB SDD, specifically a [Crucial BX500](https://www.crucial.com/products/ssd/bx500-ssd), and a pretty decent 61 key MIDI controller, a [Novation Impulse 61](https://novationmusic.com/es/node/22). The Korg M50 is still there but I have lent it to my son for his piano practices.</content><author><name>Ignacio Calvo Martínez</name><email>ignacio.calvo@gmail.com</email></author><category term="music" /><category term="studiodiary" /><category term="audio" /><category term="home" /><category term="studio" /><category term="recording" /><summary type="html">Two new additions for my home studio: a much needed 1TB SDD, specifically a Crucial BX500, and a pretty decent 61 key MIDI controller, a Novation Impulse 61. The Korg M50 is still there but I have lent it to my son for his piano practices.</summary></entry></feed>